[Music]
Hello, everyone.
TDSW YouTube Channel.
This will be the 11th episode of Getting started with GLSL on TouchDesigner.
Thank you for watching!
This time, sir.
Talk about blending at GLSL.
Eventually, as you're seeing now.
I'd like to output the pattern.
So what we're going to do this time, we're going to do some preparation.
Creating a Buffer with GLSL
Next, let's look at additive synthesis
I'm going to blend more and make various patterns!
This time I'm going to use Add, Multiply, Difference and Screen
We're going to do these four things.
So let's get to it.
Yes, we'll start this time with this situation.
This is, uh... the last part of the second episode.
This is the kind of striped image I'm going to use Sine Wave for.
I'm setting the size to 1280x720.
One important point is that this is where the Pixel Format is set to
I'm using it as a 16-bit float.
When I put out this TOP To.
As long as you get a Sine wave of -1 to 1, you're good to go
This is where the 8-bit
Perhaps this is how it's supposed to work.
It only displays values between 0 and 1.
So it's like this.
Be sure to choose 16-bit
In this case, I'm going to combine the colors in GLSL.
You can check the state of the synthesizer before the synthesis.
I'd like to see the differences in the synthesis methods at the same time
Multiple outputs from a single GLSL
We will use Buffer in this case
Use RenderSelect to output Buffer
Place the RenderSelect
Like this.
GLSL to the place where this TOP is specified.
Here you go.
We're online now.
To start, let's output the uv here
vec4 colorUV = vec4(p, 0.0, 1.0)
This is how I see it.
In order to output to this Buffer
location = 0
out vec4 color_uv
In addition, at the bottom of the main function, you'll find
With this now-declared color_uv
ColovUV with its uv specification
I think I've got the uv output for now
If this index is zero, it means that
If you set the Index 0
The color_uv of 0 specified here is
The output with this colorUV would be
It goes like this.
I'm kind of losing it now.
I'm going to output the stripes that were coming out earlier.
Place another RenderSelect in
And now I'm going to set the Index to 1
I can't see it because there's another WARNING here.
I'd like to fix this place.
Now put a second location = 1 here, and put
color_1
Additionally, color_1 equals
color and
You can put it in like this.
Now it's here, at a place called # of Color Buffers.
It's like 1 right now.
If you set this to 2, you'll get one more output
The default is 1 and I'm usually out here using fragColor.
If you select 2.
Allows output to one or more RenderSelect
That's two to go.
Buffer can now be output
There's a vertical line here, but...
Now I'd like to add a horizontal line.
color I'm going to rename this one
color1, color2 and
Here's color1
You don't have to use this one, so comment out.
That's one.
I'd like color1 to make a vertical line and color2 to make it a horizontal line.
Let's take the uv forward.
So, color1
Now color two. This one is color two.
Let's say y.
I'd like to output it again.
location = 2
Here's one more thing.
It goes something like this.
Add another RenderSelect
Now let's assume that the index is 2
If I turn this place to three this time, a horizontal line comes in.
Next, we add these together and output the result
Let's get rid of this fragColor this time because it doesn't have to be separate
I'll turn it off.
Once the code is cleaned up.
with the following location = 3
color_add
Again, color_add
You didn't declare it.
colorAdd is in.
This add is simply
color1.rgb and
color2.rgb and
Add another RenderSelect to the
Three, this is four.
This is how you do it.
This way, for some reason.
I'm starting to see these little interesting shapes.
I'm not sure why the result of adding these vertical and horizontal lines is this.
I thought it was really strange at first, too.
I'd like to explain a little bit about why this is happening.
First of all, this sine curve...
I was putting it out there earlier, but if you look at the Top To.
Let's cross out the g, b and a.
It's shaped like this.
It's like a change from -1 to 1.
But this black spot, you see.
So there's a number below zero in there.
If you go from this area, it's going from 0 to -1 and then 0.
That's why you're more likely to be in a black area.
The same black will have different values in it.
In this case.
We're taking these values in the x-direction right now.
It's always a constant value.
Let's add these two together in Math CHOP
Add in Combine CHOPs
It goes something like this.
This place you're looking at right now is a complete zero.
So it's somewhere around here.
It doesn't affect me in any way.
It's the exact same number.
I'm going to change this position a bit.
The 0.5 is also in the middle.
I'd like to link this and this first.
I hope so.
Okay, here we go.
If you move this around, you'll see that the value changes a little bit.
For example, this.
Around here, around here, it's around 0.7.
It's all white around here.
It's got a number close to 1 in it, though.
Let's take a look around 0.7.
That's about it.
ここを見たときにほとんどが0から1の間に入ってて
この黒のあたり
黒になるエリアがほぼないんですね
これがこのaddした時にいう
この辺なんですね0.7
この辺のことを言うわけです
白のエリアがこう多くて黒のエリアはここだけ
0.7 白がここと こういう風になってます
これがこのサイクルですね
例えばこの辺がどういう値かというとvが0.3あたりですね
0.3あたりというのはこうなっていて
ほぼ全部0より下にあるという風になってますので
ここも真っ暗となっていますね
ここに例え白があったとしてもこの黒の値の方が大きくて
黒のマイナスの値の方が大きいので結果は黒になってしまうと
こういう風になります
これとここからこのaddから出したTOP To
これは
0.324一緒なので
これとこれが全く同じものになるわけですね
これがいわゆる加算合成というやつになります
次はMultiply掛け算を出力していきたいと思います
Mutiply
Mutiplyなので単純にこれはかけてるんですね
color1.rgb * color2.rgbとなります
こんな感じですね
もう1個新しく作って
今度はこれはIndexは4
こちらは
GLSLのここを5にすると
こうすると
今度は掛け算をするとこういう風になるんですね
また違った模様が現れてきました
これもですね加算と一緒で
こうやって計算をした結果こういう
パターンが生まれてくるということになります
次はDifferenceを出してみたいと思います
これは絶対値ですね
color1からcolor2を引いた数の絶対値を取るというやつです
Differenceの
こうですねこれでもう一個
これを6にするとまた違ったパターンが出てきました
面白いですね
これも同様に
この加算と同じように計算して出すことができます
もう気づきの方もおられると思うんですけどもこれらの
AddとかMutiplyとかDifferenceっていうのは
TouchDesignerのComposite TOPで全部再現できるんですね
これと同じことをやっていると
この1と2を持っていって
これが最初のデフォルトなのでMultiplyですよね
これが入ってきて
これがAddだったらこれになって
これがDifferenceだったらこれが出てくるという風になってますね
このComposite TOPは全GLSLで再現できるということができます
僕の場合なんかですねPhotoshopとかで
何となくこんな感じの出力がされるんだろうなぁと思って
ブレンドモードとか使ってましたけど
こうやって改めて数値で理解できるとすごい面白いなぁと
勉強している時に思った記憶があります
今までの3つはすごい単純なものだったんですけども
実装のアルゴリズムがぱっと思いつかない物ってけっこうあると思うんですね
例えば今からスクリーンモードを実装したいんですけども
どんなことになっているんだろうと思ってですね
こうやってAdobeのページに行くと
スクリーンの項については各チャンネル内のcolor情報に基づき
合成色と基本色を反転したカラーを乗算しますと
こういう風になっていますね
これをGLSLで書くと
ちょっと書いていきます
vec3 blendScreen(vec3 base, vec3 blend)
vec3 color = base * (1 - blend) + blend
return color
こうです何かカミスってますね
これで関数が書けました
で今度も
これを新しく出力したいので
color_screen
color_screenがあって
color_screenをここで使っていきます
blendScreen(color1.rgb, color2.rgb)
こういう形になりますね
今度はこのscreenも出力したいので
出していきます
Screenでやるとこれまた別のパターンが
こうやって現れてくることになります
画像を入力してみたいと思います
Movie File Inでこう
ここではcolor1に入れましょうか
texture(sTD2DInputs[0], vUV.st)
バナナが入りましたね
ここで4つを比較すると
せっかくなのでですねちょっとこれに動きをつけていきます
2個目に動きをつけていきましょうか
2個目なのでこれにuTimeとかつけると
存在しないのでエラーがでます
こうですね
まだこの変数を持っていないので入ってもらって
absTime.frame/10とか
こんな感じで写真と一緒にやってもこういう違いが出てきて
面白いんじゃないかと思います
またパターンに戻しましょう
こうですね
別々のパターンがこうやって生まれてくるのがわかると思います
これで4種類の異なるパターンを作ることができたので
最初にお見せしたものとだいたい
同じものができたんじゃないかなと思います
この値を色々変えたりして
お気に入りのパターンを生成してみてください
今回ちょっと趣向を変えまして
ここからちょっと僕のフリースタイルで
どんなパターンが作れるのか
いろいろコードを書いていってみたいと思います
この先コードの解説はありません
こんな感じですね
色々いじってみると
何か面白いおもしろいパターンが生まれてくることもあると思いますので
皆さんもいろいろやってみてください
今回はここまでになります
TDSWでは毎月2回程度
週末にライブ配信ワークショップを行っています
チケットはPeatixやEventbriteからお求めいただけます
またPatreonも利用しています
現在こちらの3つのプランがあります
これらのリンクは動画の概要欄にありますので
よかったらチェックしてみてください
それではご視聴ありがとうございました
気に入っていただけたらグッドボタンと
チャンネル登録よろしくお願いいたします
ではまた
[音楽]